Guide to the George Aust Papers OSB MSS 270
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
George Aust papers
1746-1837
1762-1827
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Aust, George, 1741-1829
OSB MSS 270
7.5 Linear Feet (10 boxes)
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Arthur Freeman on the James Marshall and Marie-Louise Osborn Collection Fund, 2002.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: I. Professional Papers, 1763-1827. II. Personal Papers, 1746-1837. III. Correspondence and Other Papers, 1762-1815. IV. Collection Inventories, undated.
George Aust (1741-1829)
George Aust was an English civil servant in the office of the Secretary of State in Great Britain during the reign of King George III. He was born in 1741 near Bath, England. After moving to London, he began his government career in 1763 as a clerk for the Northern Department of the Secretary of State, which would be reorganized as the Foreign Office in 1782. Aust was promoted to senior clerk in 1780 and appointed deputy writer of the official government journal London Gazette by 1781. In 1790, he was appointed Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, a position shared with Sir James Bland Burges, where Aust's responsibilities included the fiscal administration of the Secret Service under Lord William Wyndham Grenville, then Foreign Secretary. Upon retirement in 1796, Aust was appointed Commissary General of Musters and Secretary to the Trustees of Royal Hospital Chelsea, and later served as Secretary to the Westminster Hospital until 1826.
Aust was married three times and remained childless. Little is known about his first wife, who died in 1803. In November 1803, Aust married Sarah Murray (1744-1811), a topographical writer who published two travel books about Scotland. Sarah was previously married to William Murray, son of the third Earl of Dunmore, from 1783 until his death in 1786. Aust subsequently married Catherine Feaver in 1813. He lived in the West End and Chelsea districts of London, where he died in 1829.
Associated Materials
George Aust papers concerning the Secret Service, 1794-1800 (OSB MSS 148). Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University.
Scope and Contents
The George Aust Papers consists of professional papers, legal and financial records, professional and personal correspondence, and other documents pertaining to the life and work of British civil servant George Aust. Aust's papers document his career of over fifty years in government service, including his position as Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs from 1790 to 1796. Correspondents include his wife Sarah Murray Aust; William Eden, first Baron Auckland; Sir James Bland Burges; Thomas Bowdler; Lord William Wyndam Grenville; William Augustus Miles; Lady Barbara Montagu; John Osborn; Bishop Thomas Percy; Sarah Scott; and Philip Yorke, second Earl of Hardwicke. The collection spans the years 1746-1837, with the bulk of the material dating from 1762-1827.
Civil service -- Great Britain; Diplomacy; Government employees, English; Great Britain -- History -- George III, 1760-1820; Great Britain -- Officials and employees; Great Britain -- Politics and government -- 1760-1820; Account books; Account books -- Great Britain -- 19th century; Business records; Probate records; Receipts (financial records); Wills; Government employees -- Great Britain; Auckland, William Eden, Baron, 1744-1814; Aust, George, 1741-1829; Bowdler, Thomas, 1754-1825; Burges, James Bland, Sir, 1752-1824; Grenville, William Wyndham Grenville, Baron, 1759-1834; Hardwicke, Philip Yorke, Earl of, 1720-1790; Miles, William Augustus, 1753?-1817; Montagu, Barbara, -1765; Murray, Sarah, 1744-1811; Osborn, John, 1743-1814; Percy, Thomas, 1729-1811; Scott, Sarah, 1720-1795; Great Britain. Foreign Office -- Officials and employees; Royal Hospital (Chelsea, London, England); Westminster Hospital
- Professional Papers, 1763–1827; 1; 2.5 Linear Feet (3 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Professional Papers consists of documents related to Aust's civil service career in the Secretary of State for the Northern Department (which became the Foreign Office in 1782) from 1763 to 1796, particularly his appointment as Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, as well as later positions at the Commissary General of Musters office, Royal Hospital Chelsea, and the Westminster Hospital. Files include official documents, drafts, memoranda, lists, administrative records, financial records, salary negotiations, and professional correspondence concerning diplomatic work, foreign affairs, politics, the military, and veteran's pensions. Correspondents include diplomats, statesmen, and other government officials, such as Lord William Wyndham Grenville, then Foreign Secretary; Sir James Bland Burges; and William Eden, first Baron Auckland.
  "The diamond snuffbox affair," as documented in the collection inventory in Series IV, refers to an incident during Aust's tenure as Under-Secretary of State, wherein fellow Under-Secretary Sir James Bland Burges received a cash gift and diamond-studded snuffbox in an exchange of diplomatic gifts with Russia, while Aust received nothing.
  Arrangement
  Arranged in chronological order, with files grouped by office held. Correspondence is filed at the end of the sequence.
  - Secretary of State for the Northern Department and Foreign Office
    - "Titles of Foreign Princes as addressed by His Majesty," and "Forms of the Address and Superscription used by His Majesty in his Cachette Letters to the several Crowned Heads and Princes of Europe", 1763, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - "A Bishop's Oath of Allegiance," draft, [1779?] (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 108)
    - Letters from William Eden, first Baron Auckland, with letters from Francis Freeling, Lord Grenville, Viscount Bute, and Sir James Marriott, 1791–1800 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - "The diamond snuffbox affair," concerning gifts from Catherine the Great to English diplomats, with letters from Sir James Bland Burges, and Louis Dutens, 1795–1796 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Commissary General of Musters office, 1796–1827, undated (Box 1, Folder 4-9)
  - Commissary General of Musters office, 1805 (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 107)
  - Commissary General of Musters, on account of fees and contingencies of the said office, 1812–1818 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Royal Hospital Chelsea, 1808–1814, undated (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
  - Royal Hospital Chelsea, 1807 (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 109)
  - Royal Hospital Chelsea, supplications by or on behalf of military men, 1795–1826, undated (Box 2, Folder 13-15)
  - The Westminster Hospital, 1823–1826, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Salary negotiations with the War Department, with letters from Lord Palmerston and Nicholas Vansittart, 1812–1822, undated (Box 2, Folder 17-19)
  - Correspondence
    - Letter from Morton Eden, first Baron Henley, 1793 June 15 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Letter from Sir Richard Clayton, 1797 November 10 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Letter from John Waliot, with mention of Napoleon Bonaparte, 1802 February 21 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Letter from George Aust to George Canning, 1804 November 8 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Letters from Robert Jocelyn, Earl of Roden, and John Dalrymple, sixth Earl of Stair, 1805 September 25–1805 November 1 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Letter from Sir Robert Liston, 1811 March 6 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Letters from Edward Stanley, and family, 1815–1816 (Box 2, Folder 26-27)
- Personal Papers, 1746–1837; 2; 1.25 Linear Feet (3 boxes)
  Personal Papers consists of records concerning Aust's roles as trustee and executor, personal financial records, and charity subscriptions. Materials include wills and related legal documents, account books, household expenses, subscriptions for newspapers and journals, bills, and receipts. The series also includes personal correspondence, and a small selection of Aust's literary writings.
  Arranged by subject, reflecting the order found at time of acquisition.
  - Estates, trusts, and wills
    - Hammond, Ann Francis, 1802–1827 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Rolleston, G.W., 1802–1826, undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Woodford, Sir Ralph, and family, 1808–1812, undated (Box 2, Folder 30-32)
    - Woodford, Sir Ralph, and family, 1778–1812 (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 110)
  - Personal financial records
    - Account book, 1787–1794 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Account book, 1793–1802 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Account book, 1795–1802 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Account book, 1812–1818 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Account book, 1818–1822 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Account with Thomas Hammond, 1799–1801 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Account with Thomas Lockington, 1801–1804 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Business with Thrupp and Son, 1812–1817, undated (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Business with Thrupp and Son, 1811–1819 (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 111)
    - Debt booklet, "W. Fraser", 1789 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Finance booklet, 1815 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Mortgage with Cooper Crawford, undated (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 112)
    - Newspaper account book, 1765–1774 (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - Receipts, 1814–1827, undated (Box 4, Folder 44)
    - Unsorted accounting, 1785–1824, undated (Box 4, Folder 45-46)
    - Unsorted correspondence, bills, and receipts, 1746–1837, undated (Box 4, Folder 47-52)
    - Unsorted correspondence, bills, and receipts, 1775–1815, 1837 (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 113)
    - Unsorted correspondence, bills, and receipts, vellum, 1808 (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 114)
  - Charities, 1801–1827 (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Charities, 1801–1827 (Box 5, Folder 54-55)
  - Letters from Robertson, William Philip Colyear, 1806–1816 (Box 5, Folder 56-57)
  - Letter from Brooke, Samuel, 1824 December 9 (Box 5, Folder 58)
  - Letter from "Miss Dee" on behalf of Maria, Duchess of Gloucester, 1807 July 8 (Box 5, Folder 59)
  - Prospectus by Butler, Reverend Weedon, circa 1790 (Box 5, Folder 60)
  - Lists of visitors to Staffa and Iona, circa 1808 (Box 5, Folder 61)
  - Autograph manuscript verses for the birthday of Francis Osborne, fifth Duke of Leeds, circa 1797 (Box 5, Folder 62)
  - Schedule to two houses, no. 7 and 8, Paradise Row, Chelsea, 1805 March 15 (Box 5, Folder 63)
  - Unsorted personal correspondence, 1796–1827, undated (Box 5, Folder 64-65a)
- Correspondence and Other Papers, 1762–1815; 3; 3.75 Linear Feet (4 boxes)
  This series contains correspondence and personal and professional papers of Sarah Murray Aust, George Aust's second wife, and others. Most of the correspondence is addressed to George Aust. Sarah Aust's papers consist of personal letters, financial records, legal records concerning her first husband William Murray, as well as drafts, publishing correspondence, and accounts with printers and booksellers related to her travel writing.
  The series also contains letters from diplomat John Osborn, and a related collection of "Osborniana," including letters to Aust from Osborn's brother, Sir George Osborn, and Osborn's wills and estate documents. Additional correspondents are philanthropist and literary editor Thomas Bowdler; writers William Augustus Miles and Bishop Thomas Percy; philanthropist Lady Barbara Montagu; novelist Sarah Scott; and statesman Philip Yorke, second Earl of Hardwicke.
  Arranged alphabetically by last name.
  - Aust, Sarah Murray
    - General papers, 1799–1812, undated (Box 5, Folder 66-68)
    - General papers, 1811–1812, undated (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 115)
    - Account book, executorship of William Murray's estate, 1786–1811 (Box 6, Folder 69)
    - Account book, 1804–1811 (Box 6, Folder 70)
    - Account book, 1809 (Box 6, Folder 71)
    - Account book, 1810 (Box 6, Folder 72)
    - Notes on minerals, autograph manuscript, undated (Box 6, Folder 73)
    - Probate of the Will of the Honorable William Murray, 1787 (Box 10 (Oversize), Folder 116)
    - Release of sums appointed by the will of the late Mrs. Aust, 1812 January 29 (Box 10 (Oversize), Folder 117)
    - "A short descriptive arrangement of Gems, stones and spars, Earths metals and semi metals," autograph manuscript, undated (Box 6, Folder 74)
  - Bowdler, Thomas, 1810–1811 (Box 6, Folder 75)
  - Miles, William Augustus, 1776–1808 (Box 7, Folder 76-77)
  - Montagu, Lady Barbara, 1762, 1764 (Box 7, Folder 78)
  - Osborn, John, 1799–1814 (Box 7, Folder 79-82)
  - Osborniana
    - Letters from Sir George Osborn, and Count Semyon Vorontsov [Woronzow], regarding the prisoner-of-war affair, 1803 (Box 7, Folder 83)
    - Letters from Sir George Osborn, regarding message from John Osborn relating to Catherine the Great, 1809 July (Box 7, Folder 84)
    - Letters from John Miliquet, 1807–1809 (Box 7, Folder 85)
    - Letters from Heneage Osborn, Thomas Metcalfe, and Mr. Luntly, financial agent, regarding Luntly's frauds, 1810–1811 (Box 7, Folder 86-87)
    - Letters from Sir George Osborn and other correspondents, regarding Patent Customers at Custom House, Cardiff, 1812–1813 (Box 7, Folder 88-90)
    - Draft will, Additional Codicils, and Minutes of the Will and Codicils of John Osborn Esquire, 1810–1814 (Box 7, Folder 91)
    - Executorship of estate, 1814–1815 (Box 7, Folder 92)
    - Unsorted correspondence and documents, 1802–1815, undated (Box 8, Folder 93-94)
  - Percy, Bishop Thomas
    - Autograph letters, signed (#1–9), 1800–1804 (Box 8, Folder 95)
    - Dictated letters, signed (#10–31), 1804–1811 (Box 8, Folder 96-98)
    - Insertions and associated material (#32–44), 1801–1811, undated (Box 8, Folder 99-100)
  - Scott, Sarah, circa 1760s–1790s (Box 8, Folder 101-104)
  - Yorke, Philip, second Earl of Hardwicke, 1778–1787 (Box 8, Folder 105)
- Collection Inventories, undated; 4
  Two inventories prepared for the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library contain detailed descriptions of the collection's materials, providing historical context and biographical information about Aust and his correspondents.
  - Inventories, undated (Box 8, Folder 106)